Finding Aid for Douglas F. Roby papers, 1914-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Douglas F. Roby papers 1914-2003, 1965-1985
Roby, Douglas F. (Douglas Fergusson), 1898-1992.
1 oversize folder
8.3 linear feet (in 9 boxes) including oversize
9768 Aa 2; UAl
Douglas Fergusson Roby was a member of the International Olympic Committee from 1952-1985 and president of the United States Olympic Committee from 1965 to 1969. The collection includes materials related to his professional activities and interests and contains personal files, national and international Olympic and athletic organizations' files and photographs, as well as Roby's personal files and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Hermine Klingler (donor no. 8114 ) in February, 1997 and March 2013.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Douglas Fergusson Roby was born on March 24, 1898 in Port Tobacco, Maryland. In 1903 the family moved to Chicago, Ill. Roby attended Wendell Phillips High School in Chicago and the Michigan Military Academy in Brighton where he excelled at football and was recruited by Phillips University in Enid, Oklahoma in 1917. After attending Phillips, Roby transferred to the University of Michigan in February 1920, where he became a member of the Pi Delta Theta fraternity. In 1921 and 1922 he played on the university baseball team as a leftfielder and on the football team as a fullback. In 1923 he was inducted into Michigamua. Roby graduated from the University of Michigan with a degree in Business Administration in 1923.
After graduation, in 1923, Roby played football as a tailback for Cleveland Indians. He also played squash for the city of Detroit in 1928-1936, winning the national championship in 1932.
In 1934, he joined American Metal Products Company, an automobile parts supplier. Roby was elected president of the company in 1954, and retired as board chairman in 1963. In the course of his career he was on the board of other companies including, First Federal Savings and Loan of Detroit and Kelsey Hayes Wheel Company.
In addition to his business connections in Detroit, he was actively involved in the civic life of the city. Most notable are his efforts to bring the Olympics to Detroit. The city made several attempts, from 1944 to 1972, to get the games. Roby was prominent in each of these attempts. He also served as a member of the Detroit Arts Commission, a member of the Board of Directors of the Detroit Zoological Society and a trustee of Harper-Grace Hospitals.
Roby was very active in amateur athletic associations. From 1951 to 1953, he was elected president of the Amateur Athletic Union (AAU) of the United States. He served as president of the Pan Am Games from 1955 to 1960. Roby was vice president of the United States Olympic Committee (USOC) from 1953 to 1965 and served as its president from 1965 to 1968. At the 1952 Olympic Games, Roby was elected to the International Olympic Committee (IOC), to be one of two IOC American members. He resigned from IOC in 1985 and from USOC in 1986.
Roby was in the center of several controversies during his tenure as the U.S. Olympics official. During the 1968 Summer Olympics in Mexico City, as the USOC president, he ordered removal of Tommie Smith and John Carlos, two African-American athletes, from the U.S. Olympic team. The punishment came after Smith and Carlos raised black-gloved fists and bowed their heads while the national anthem of the United States was played during a medal ceremony. In 1979 Roby voted against the People's Republic of China's readmission to the Olympics (China was readmitted). In 1984 he unsuccessfully advocated for readmission of South Africa.
Roby died in April 1992 in Ann Arbor, Michigan.
This collection is divided into three series: Personal/Biographical, Olympic Games, and Photographs and photo albums. Personal/Biographical (1922-2003, 1 linear foot) series contains material concerning Roby's early life and business activities, as well as speeches, writings, and a scrapbook. The Olympic Games (1948-1988, 6 linear feet) series is the largest series in the collection and encompasses Roby's activities in various national and international sports associations. The Photographs and photo albums (1914-1989, 1.3 linear feet) series contains photographs from throughout Roby's life.
Subjects:
Roby, Douglas F. (Douglas Fergusson), 1898-1992.; Olympics.; Sports.; Sports officials--United States.; United States Olympic Committee.; International Olympic Committee.; Amateur Athletic Union of the United States.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Roby, Douglas F. (Douglas Fergusson), 1898-1992.; University of Michigan.; International Olympic Committee.; United States Olympic Committee.; Amateur Athletic Union of the United States.
Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.; Photo albums.; Photographs.
- Personal/Biographical
  Found here is material related to his years at the University of Michigan and Phillips University in Enid, Oklahoma. He was prominent in the athletic programs of both schools as a student. Roby also took an active interest in the affairs of the schools as an alumnus. The bulk of the material related to his years as a student concerns his relationship with the University of Michigan.
  A small selection of correspondence and clippings reflect on Roby's activities at American Metal Products in Detroit as well as his activities with Detroit based businesses First Federal Savings and Loan and Kelsey Hayes Wheel Company.
  Speeches and articles are included as are publications which mention him prominently. Of particular note is a scrapbook containing clippings and photographs from 1950 to 1972. In 1987, Roby's daughter Hermine Roby Klingler complied The Personal History of Douglas Fergusson Roby, a collection of photographs and text about Roby's life. This volume is cataloged separately in the Bentley Historical Library's holdings (call no. DB 2 R668 A12).
  The Personal/ Biographical series includes material related to Roby's civic activities for the city of Detroit: his tenure on the Detroit Arts Commission and activities in the Detroit Athletic Club (DAC). Also included material related to the honors and awards received by Roby, biographical information, newspaper clippings, and obituaries.
  - Awards and Honors 1940-1986 (Box 1)
  - Biographical information (Box 1)
  - Business
    - American Metal Products
      - Clippings 1953-1957 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1954-1980 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous undated (Box 1)
    - First Federal Savings 1966-1974 (Box 1)
    - Kelsey-Hayes Wheel Company 1967-1972 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1950-1981 (Box 1)
  - Detroit
    - Detroit Arts Commission 1954-1973, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Detroit Athletic Club (DAC) 1958-1990, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan Military Academy 1966 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1957-1983, 1990-2003 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings 1940-1996 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries 1992 (Box 1)
  - Phillips University 1963-1978 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 1950-1972 (Box 1)
  - Speeches and Writings 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan
    - Art Museum Council 1976-1979 (Box 1)
    - Athletics 1922-1982 (Box 1)
    - Clippings 1922-1972 (Box 1)
    - Michigamua 1923-1978 (Box 1)
    - Reunions 1936-1989, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Olympic Games
  The Olympic Games series is the largest series in the collection and encompasses Roby's activities in various national and international sports associations, including the Amateur Athletic Association, the U.S. Olympic Committee, and the International Olympic Committee. This series also includes material related to individual Olympic Games and Pan American Games, Olympic bids --specifically, Detroit and Los Angeles,--and various issues that arose in preparation to and during Olympiads.
  - Amateur Athletic Union (Box 2)
    A large portion of the Amateur Athletic Association material is related to the AAU/NCAA controversy; also included general correspondence, clippings and publications.
    - AAU-NCAA controversy
      - 1948-1950 (Box 2)
      - 1962-1965 (Box 2)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 2)
      - 1968-1970 (Box 2)
      - 1971-1975 (Box 2)
      - 1976 (Box 2)
      - 1977 (Box 2)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
      - 1980-1981, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Clippings 1956-1965 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - 1963-1974 scattered (Box 2)
      - 1977-1981 (Box 2)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - Publications 1952, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Detroit Olympic Bids
    The Detroit Olympic bids is a small collection of articles, clippings, and some correspondence related to the city's unsuccessful 1952-1972 Summer Olympics campaigns.
    - 1952 Olympics-Summer, 1946 (Box 2)
    - 1960 Olympics-Summer, 1955 (Box 2)
    - 1964 Olympics-Summer, undated (Box 2)
    - 1968 Olympics-Summer
      - Clippings 1962-1963 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1962-1966 (Box 2)
      - Reports 1962-1963 (Box 2)
    - 1972 Olympics-Summer, 1966 (Box 2)
  - International Olympic Committee
    The International Olympic Committee is the largest part of the series. It include administrative files of the Committee: correspondence, minutes, reports and resolutions of general IOC Sessions, the Executive Board, and various IOC committees.
    - Clippings 1956-1980 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - 1964-1965 (Box 2)
      - 1966 (Box 2)
      - 1967 (Box 2)
      - 1968 (Box 2)
      - 1969 (Box 2)
      - 1970-1971 (Box 2)
      - 1972 (Box 2)
      - 1973 (Box 2)
      - 1974 (Box 2)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
      - 1980 (Box 2)
      - 1981-1983 (Box 2)
      - 1984-1986 (Box 2)
    - Meetings and reports (Box 3)
      - 62nd Session minutes (Tokyo, Japan, 1964) (Box 3)
      - 64th Session 1966
        - Lausanne, Switzerland (Box 3)
        - Rome, Italy (Box 3)
      - 73rd Session minutes (Munich, West Germany, 1972) (Box 3)
      - 75th Session minutes (Vienna, Austria, 1974) (Box 3)
      - 76th Session minutes (Lausanne, Switzerland, 1975) (Box 3)
      - 77th Session minutes (Innsbruck, Austria, 1976) (Box 3)
      - 79th Session minutes (Prague, Czechoslovakia, 1977) (Box 3)
      - 81st Session minutes (Montevideo, Uruguay, 1979) (Box 3)
      - 82nd Session modifications to the Olympic Charter (Lake Placid, USA, 1980) (Box 3)
      - 83rd Session minutes (Moscow, USSR, 1980) (Box 3)
      - 84th Session (Baden Baden, West Germany, 1981)
        - Meeting material (Box 3)
        - Meeting minutes (Box 3)
      - 85th Session materials, various cities, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 86th Session correspondence (New Delhi, India, 1983) (Box 3)
      - 89th Session minutes (Lausanne, Switzerland, 1984) (Box 3)
      - Analyses of daily press comment August-September, 1973 (Box 3)
      - Awards Commission meeting minutes 1974 (Box 3)
      - Cultural Commission meeting minutes 1974 (Box 3)
      - Eligibility Commission meeting minutes 1974 (Box 3)
      - Emblems Commission meeting minutes 1974 (Box 3)
      - Executive Board 1964-1975 with gaps, 9 folders (Box 3)
      - Executive Board 1976-1984 with gaps, 6 folders (Box 4)
      - Finance Commission meeting minutes 1974 (Box 4)
      - General review of the sports, events, competitors, and medal distribution in the Olympic Games... report, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
      - International Olympic Academy Commission meeting minutes 1974-1975 (Box 4)
      - IOC meeting in Amsterdam, The Netherlands 1970 (Box 4)
      - IOC meeting in Luxemburg 1971 (Box 4)
      - IOC meeting in Tehran, Iran 1967 (Box 4)
      - IOC report 1974 (Box 4)
      - Medical Commission meeting minutes 1974 (Box 4)
      - National Olympic Committees meeting September 1971 (Box 4)
      - Press analysis, June / July and September, 1975 (Box 4)
      - Press Commission meeting minutes 1974-1975, 1977, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Programme Commission
        - Joint IOC/NOC Commission for the Olympic Programme report 1972 (Box 4)
        - Meeting minutes 1974 (Box 4)
      - Publications Commission meeting minutes 1974-1975 (Box 4)
      - Solidarity Commission meeting minutes and report 1974 (Box 4)
      - Subjects raised by IOC sessions since 1941, 1972 report (Box 4)
      - Tripartite Commission meeting minutes 1974-1976 (Box 4)
      - Television Commission meeting minutes 1977 (Box 4)
      - Television Sub-Committee and representatives of the Lake Placid Bid Committee meeting minutes 1974 (Box 4)
    - Publications 1950s-1960s (Box 4)
    - Subject files
      Subject files include Roby's correspondence with IOC presidents Avery Brundage, Michael Morris (Lord Killanin), and Juan Antonio Samaranch, as well as material on specific topics, such as China and South Africa's readmission to the Olympics, among others.
      - Berlioux, Monique 1976-1983, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Brundage, Avery 1959-1979 scattered (Box 4)
      - Eligibility rules 1968, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
      - Flag etiquette 1970, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Henning, Harold W. 1974-1978 (Box 4)
      - International Olympic Academy 1966-1973, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Israeli Olympic Fund 1972 (Box 4)
      - Killanin, Michael Morris (Lord Killanin) 1972-1980, 7 folders (Box 4)
      - People's Republic of China 1965-1981 with gaps, 4 folders (Box 4)
      - Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty 1976, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Roosevelt, Julian K. 1973-1985, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Samaranch, Jose Antonio 1980-1984, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - South Africa 1967-1979 with gaps, 5 folders (Box 5)
      - Virgin Islands Olympic Committee 1966-1967 (Box 5)
      - World Sports Foundation 1972-1974 (Box 5)
  - Olympiads
    The Olympiads material includes correspondence and documentation related to Olympic bids, organization, and issues. For example, the 1968 Summer Olympic Games in Mexico material contains a "Smith and Carlos incident" folder; material related to the 1980 Moscow Summer Games includes discussion of the Games boycott by the United States. Also of significance is material related to organization of the 1980 Winter Olympic Games in Lake Placid and of the 1984 Summer Olympic Games in Los Angeles.
    - 1968 Olympics-Summer (Mexico City, Mexico)
      - 1966, 1968 (Box 5)
      - Smith and Carlos incident (Box 5)
    - 1968 Olympics-Winter (Grenoble, France), 1966-1968 (Box 5)
    - 1972 Olympics
      - General information 1970-1972 (Box 5)
      - Summer Olympics (Munich, West Germany) 1971-1974 (Box 5)
      - Winter Olympics (Sapporo, Japan) 1971-1972, 1978 (Box 5)
    - 1976 Olympics-Summer (Montreal, Canada)
      - 1967-1976 with gaps, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Los Angeles bid 1968-1970 (Box 5)
    - 1976 Olympics-Winter (Innsbruck, Austria), 1966-1968, 1975-1976, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - 1980 Olympics-Summer (Moscow, USSR), 1973-1980 with gaps, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - 1980 Olympics-Winter (Lake Placid, USA), 1972-1983 with gaps, 7 folders (Box 6)
    - 1984 Olympics-Summer (Los Angeles, USA), 1978-1986, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - 1988 Olympics-Winter (Calgary, Canada), 1982, 1988 (Box 6)
    - Pan American Games 1954-1971 scattered (Box 6)
  - Subject files
    The Olympic Games Subject Files contain correspondence with individuals and on topics, such as Special Olympics and President's Commission on Olympic Sports, among others.
    - Amateur Athletic Act (S. 3500) (Box 6)
    - Barnes, Everett D. 1968-1969 (Box 6)
    - Buck, Clifford H. 1966-1974 with gaps (Box 6)
    - deCapriles, Miguel 1967-1978 with gaps (Box 6)
    - Dodson, Joyce (The Dodson case) 1966-1970 (Box 6)
    - Jim Thorpe Foundation 1977, 1982-1984 (Box 6)
    - Krumm, Philip H. 1973-1976, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Lentz, Arthur G. 1967-1968 (Box 6)
    - Miller, F. Don 1969-1982, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Olympic House 1965-1968, 1972-1975, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - President's Commission on Olympic Sports 1975-1978 (Box 7)
    - Senate Commerce Committee Hearings 1973 (Box 7)
    - Special Olympics 1968-1971, 1974 (Box 7)
    - Sullivan, Patrick H. 1965-1969, 1972-1988 scattered (Box 7)
    - The Athletic Congress (TAC) 1982-1983 (Box 7)
    - U.S. Women's Basketball Team tour of South America 1970 (Box 7)
  - U.S. Olympics Committee
    The U.S. Olympic Committee material includes correspondence and meetings minutes, reports and resolutions.
    - Clippings 1946-1985, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Correspondence
      - 1951-1959 scattered (Box 7)
      - 1963-1966 (Box 7)
      - 1967-1969 (Box 7)
      - 1970 (Box 7)
      - 1971 (Box 7)
      - 1972 (Box 7)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 7)
      - 1976-1986 (Box 7)
    - Meetings and reports
      - 1963, 1965 (Box 7)
      - 1972 (Box 7)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 7)
      - 1981 (Box 7)
      - 1982 (Box 7)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 7)
- Photographs and photo albums
  The bulk of the material is personal photographs depicting Roby with friends and associates, high school and university class and sports team photos, as well as Roby's University of Michigan scrapbook. Also included photographs from sports associations of which he was a member and sporting events that he helped to plan. The series includes images of renowned athletes and sports figures, as well as political leaders, such as Jesse Owens, Fielding H. Yost, Franklin Cappon, Jim Ryun, George Romney, Prince Gholam Reza Pahlavi, among others. Also found here are photographs collected for use in The Personal History of Douglas Fergusson Roby. Of note is an undated outsize view of the Ohio State University stadium, autographed by Fielding H. Yost on the back side.
  - Advisory Panel on International Athletics 1965 (Box 8)
  - Amateur Athletic Union
    - 1974 (Box 8)
    - National Amateur Athletic Union Women's and Men's Swimming Championships 1951 (Box 8)
  - Awards and Honors
    - 1971-1972 (Box 8)
    - Undated (Box 8)
  - Detroit
    - Detroit Arts Commission 1969 (Box 8)
    - Detroit Athletic Club (DAC) 1944-1972, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Detroit Olympic Committee 1964, undated (Box 8)
  - International Olympic Committee 1956-1982 (Box 8)
  - Pan American Games undated (Box 8)
  - Personal
    - 1916-1936 (Box 8)
    - 1950-1959, 1976 (Box 8)
    - 1987, 1989 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Military Academy 1916 (Box 8)
    - Phillips University 1919-1977 (Box 8)
    - Photographs for The Personal History of Douglas Fergusson Roby, 1987 (Box 8)
    - University of Michigan
      - 1921-1972 (Box 8)
      - Michiganesian (negatives) 1922-1923 (Box 8)
    - Wendell Phillips High School 1915 (Box 8)
    - Undated (Box 8)
  - United States Olympic Committee
    - 1967-1969 (Box 8)
    - United States Olympic Swimming Finals 1948 (Box 8)
    - Undated (Box 8)
  - Unidentified events (Box 8)
  - First Federal Savings and Loan of Detroit Board of Directors 1976 (Box 9)
  - Forestville School 1914 (Box 9)
  - IOC Diploma 1967 (Box 9)
  - Pictorial memories of the 54th Session of I.O.C., May 1958 Tokyo photo album and loose photo album pages (Box 9)
  - Roby, Douglas F. undated (Box 9)
  - Squaw Valley-Lake Tahoe: California's choice for the 1960 Winter Olympics photo album and loose photo album pages (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan
    - Scrapbook and loose scrapbook pages (Box 9)
    - Photographs 1921-1922 (Box 9)
  - Wendell Phillips High School photographs 1914-1916 (Box 9)
  - Unidentified and undated school photograph (Box 9)
  - View of the Ohio State University stadium, autographed by Fielding H. Yost undated (Folder 1)